Leo Hurwitz collection, 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991
George Eastman Museum
- Series 3, Film/TV Projects, 1930-1991; 1936-1987
  - Subseries 23, Native Land, 1930-1989; 1936-1951
    - no title (Box C029)
      - [Unlabeled binder containing Native Land material], 1938-1940 (Folder 1)
        Zippered binder containing material related to the production of Native Land including a notebook labeled "N.L. Notes" with notes on camera shots and a cost sheet for 1938-1939; two copies of a "reading script" by Hurwitz, Paul Strand, and David Wolff [Ben Maddow] titled "The Story of Production #5"; a folder titled "L.H. Notes and Outlines in Front Pocket of Script," containing notes, a draft outline of Native Land, and a commentary by Hurwitz written during the production of the film; an unlabeled manila envelope containing additional notes, outline draft, and storyboards; and graph paper with reel sequences, commentary, and soundtrack log.
      - [Folder labeled:Native Land log], ca. 1940 (Folder 2)
        Log for the final cut of Native Land, consisting of sequence lists with shot number, footage, description, shot length, sound, and notes.
      - Dialogue sheets --Native Land, ca. 1940 (Folder 3)
        Contains two copies of the Native Land dialogue sheets.
      - [Shoebox labeled: Letters 1940s], 1941-1955 (Folder Box 1)
    - no title (Box C033)
      - Current correspondence -- answer!, 1961-1962; undated (Folder 1)
        Correspondence related to Here at the Waters' Edge, "The Scarlet Letter," and film elements for Native Land and China Strikes Back. Correspondents include Nazli Nour, Thomas Brandon, and Judith Gold.
      - L.H. Bonded Film Storage, 1966; 1973 (Folder 4)
      - Native Land, 1973 (Folder 24)
        Correspondence and contract regarding Radim Films, Inc.'s rerelease of Native Land; letter from Richard Roud telling Hurwitz that the rerelease would not be included in 11th New York Film Festival.
      - Native Land-- distribution & screening again, 1972-1973 (Folder 25)
        1973 letter from attorney Stanley Faulkner regarding payment for a screening of Native Land; copy of payment check; 1972 letter from the Student Assembly of Columbia University regarding screenings of Native Land.
    - no title (Box C034)
      - Native Land-- New School -- seminar in F. techniques, 1948 (Folder 1d)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's "Seminar in Film Techniques," taught at the New School of Social Research in spring 1948. Includes Film Department course description brochure, "Outline of Basic-Need Themes in the Film Native Land," and handwritten notes on Frontier Films, Inc., letterhead.
    - no title (Box C038)
      - [Correspondence], 1973-1975 (Folder 7)
        Correspondence regarding screenings and symposia at Rhode Island School of Design, John Jay College (where Native Land received a negative response), New York Film Council, Antioch College, Museum of Modern Art, University of Massachusetts Amherst; new prints of Native Land and Return to Life(a 6/24/1974 letter from Thomas Brandon mentions a 35mm print due to arrive at George Eastman House from Henri Langlois); a theatrical re-release of Native Land and recent negative reactions to the film; and the formation of limited partnership to produce the film "Shoot Film, Not People."
    - no title (Box C039)
      - [Bag labeled: Bank statements and insurance policies, etc.], 1975-1980 (Folder 1)
        Personal correspondence, including a letter from Hazel Strand regarding the rights to Paul Strand's work, and letters from Gordon Hitchens with comments from his students about Hurwitz and Native Land. Other subjects include distribution payments for Native Land.
    - no title (Box C041)
      - Native Land: re. neg. on west coast & preservation, 1989 (Folder 40)
      - Native Land-- 1989 Letters with UCLA Archive, LA Dept. of Rec. and Parks, 1983 (Folder 41)
      - Stanley Faulkner, 1973; 1976-1978 (Folder 69)
    - no title (Box C043)
      - [Native Land stills], undated (Folder 3d)
        Six black-and-white stills from Native Land.
      - Current to-do:N.L.,"S.L.",H.A.T.W.E.,M&F, misc., people to invite, 1962-1963 (Folder 3f)
    - no title (Box C055)
      - Personal, 1947 (Folder 6)
    - no title (Box C057)
      - Copies: film texts (not D.W.A.W.D.), 1980 (Folder 6)
        Native Land script, typed by Nelly Burlingham in 1980.
      - Film texts, 1964; 1966; 1980 (Folder 8)
      - [Envelope labeled: Originals and copies], 1964; 1966; 1980; undated (Folder 10)
    - no title (Box C069)
      - [Strange Victory film materials, lab work], 1977 (Folder 4)
        Invoices for lab work done on Strange Victory and Native Land and related correspondence.
    - no title (Box C073)
      - Correspondence (General), 1944-1958 (Folder 1)
        Includes correspondence regarding Columbia Studios' purchase of footage from Native Land, and a letter to the Signal Corps Photo Center regarding use of Native Land footage in their film "Your Army Today."
      - Correspondence from drawer (old), 1942-1943 (Folder 12)
        Includes correspondence between Hurwitz and Pvt. Leon Levy of the Army Service Forces regarding "Colonel [Frank] Capra"'s request to use Native Land footage.
      - Correspondence (Native Land-- 1950), 1942; 1945; 1949-1950; 1957 (Folder 16)
        Correspondence and notes concerning the distribution of Native Land, particularly the question of whether or not the film should be distributed abroad and risk "misinterpretation" or "suppressed." Correspondents include Hurwitz, Paul Strand, trustee Bernard Reis and other Native Land lenders. Included are letters regarding a lenders' meeting to decide the issue, and an exchange between Hurwitz, Strand, Reis, and Henri Langlois regarding the fate of a 16mm print of Native Land then in possession of the Cinématèque Française. Also includes a 5/17/1950 Variety clipping regarding a suit filed by Brandon Films and Bernard Reis against Film Program Services charging the wrongful distribution of Native Land; correspondence regarding the storage of Frontier Films film materials; and a to-do list for a 1942 trip to Washington D.C. In English, French, and Russian.
    - no title (Box C096)
      - [Envelope labeled: Jane's letters from Israel], 1965-1968 (Folder 10)
        Letters from Jane Dudley and others. Also includes correspondence regarding a special screening of Native Land for Paul Robeson's birthday.
      - L.H. miscellaneous, 1963 (Folder 18b)
        Includes Hurwitz's résumé; a clipping from Les Lettres Française with English translation; promotional flyers for Native Land with press clippings; notes and correspondence related to Native Land; quotes from reviews of Strange Victory.
    - no title (Box C102)
      - Rathner and Native Land and other correspondence, 1943-1949 (Folder 14)
        Correspondence regarding Native Land, including Harry Rathner's reedit and wartime distribution. Correspondents include Joris Ivens, Thomas Brandon, Jay Leyda, John Howard Lawson, George Marshall, and Ben [no last name given]. Also includes correspondence related to distribution of other Frontier Films productions.
    - no title (Box C103)
      - [Envelope labeled: Rollins material re:S.V.,N.L., & misc.], 1975 (Folder 2a)
        Several cinema-studies essays written by Prof. Peter C. Rollins and a letter to Hurwitz from Rollins regarding the screening Native Land at the 1975 American Studies Association convention.
    - no title (Box C104)
      - [Envelope labeled: Leo Hurwitz contract], 1973 (Folder 13a)
        Native Land distribution agreement with Impact Films. Includes related correspondence.
      - [Envelope labeled: Brandon stuff], 1974 (Folder 13b)
        Photocopies of the press release for "A Missing Chapter in the History of U.S. Document Films"" arranged and presented by Thomas Brandon.
    - no title (Box C186)
      - [Envelope labeled:Native Land-- work stuff for spy sequence], ca. 1938 (Folder 8)
        Notes, synopsis, and script for the sequence.
      - [Envelope labeled: Notes -- documents, production #5 --Native Land], 1936-1938 (Folder 9)
    - no title (Box C190)
      - [The Labor Spy Racket book], 1937 (Folder 1)
        By Leo Huberman. 1937 Gold Seal paperback edition.
      - [The Labor Spy book], 1934 (Folder 2)
        By Sidney Howard. 1934 Republic Publishing Company paperback edition. Fragile, back cover detached.
      - [La Follette Civil Liberties Committee hearings book], 1938 (Folder 3)
        Published book titled Violations of Free Speech and Rights of Labor -- Hearings before a Subcommittee of the Committee of Education and Labor United States Senate, Seventy-fifth Congress, Second Session, Pursuant to S. Res. 266 (74th Congress); A Resolution to Investigate violations of the Right of Free Speech and Assembly and Interference with the Right of Labor to Organize and Bargain Collectively, Part 15-A, November 18, 1937.
      - Letters to Leo, 1942-1943; 1951; 1963 (Folder 14)
      - [Leslie Fishbein --Native Land paper], 1977 (Folder 25)
        Copy of Leslie Fishbein's paper "Native Land: Document and Documentary," with cover letter and Hurwitz's response and notes.
    - no title (Box C192)
      - [Envelope labeled: Notes, etc. of '30s -- early Frontier], 1937-1939 (Folder 2b)
        Senate Report on industrial espionage, the violations of free speech and rights of labor; Frontier Films business cards in leather envelope; drafts of sequences from Native Land notes on the "SL Talk" about Frontier Films; Frontier Films by-laws; memo to John Howard Lawson and report on Frontier Films; Frontier Films statement of income and expenses; letter from the Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy, with attached cartoon drawings and outline for anti-Fascist animation idea film; statement by Joris Ivens on Paul Strand;Native Land summary; two-ring binder embossed with "Victory" on the cover containing sequences for film labeled "Prologue -- XX -- Song of the School-Children," with notes on child labor film ("Pay Day"), brochure on Frontier Films, notes on steel workers film, sketch for unnamed scenario, notes on laissez-faire, notes on school film (all tucked into the front of the binder).
      - [Native Land publicity materials], ca. 1942 (Folder 3b)
        Press book and press releases for Native Land. Museum of Modern Art Film Library film notes for series on the Russian film.
      - [Envelope labeled: Duplicate clippings (Native Land)], 1942 (Folder 3e)
        Newspaper clippings, copy of the National Board of Review Magazine and The Commonweal (articles and reviews of Native Land).
      - [Folder labeled: Farm film], 1936; 1942 (Folder 3f)
        Includes Native Land flyers.
      - [Envelope labeled: Programs and photostats of reviews of Native Land], ca. 1942 (Folder 3h)
        Programs for Native Land at the World Theatre in New York City (multiple copies) and press packet of articles, reviews, and testimonials.
      - [Envelope labeled: LTH desk stuff ($)], 1940-1942 (Folder 3i)
        Two small spiral bound notebooks, including notes on "labor morale" film, photo lecture, civil liberties film, and Paul Robeson's thoughts on Native Land; correspondence from Paul Strand regarding Native Land; pamphlets and booklets for the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO: What It Is... and How It Came to Be," "Unite for Victory," "The Church Speaks Out", "The CIO and Labor Unity," "Your Civil Liberties and How to Protect Them," "Taxes for Victory"); program for the Artists' Front to Win the War at Carnegie Hall, October 16, 1942 (with flyer for Native Land inside); pamphlet "Democracy will live or die" from July 22, 1942, rally at Madison Square Park for a Second Front, including the address given by Charlie Chaplin; draft review by Hurwitz of Eisenstein's book The Film Sense; MoMA program: "The Museum of Modern Art Film Library Repeats a Cycle of 300 Films"; three "Bulletins from Britain" and other pamphlets published by the British Library of Information.
      - [File pocket labeled: NYKino and Frontier Films -- work sheets and notes --Native Land], 1936-1939 (Folder 4)
        Synopsis and treatment for "Civil Liberties Film" (which was developed into Native Land); notes, drafts, and revisions for Native Land sequences; location schedule and lists of props for spy sequence; newspaper articles about production of the film and labor and union issues; shooting script for sequence N (Frontier Films, Production #5); notes and data on Shoemaker sequence; shooting schedules for You and Me(directed by Fritz Lang); farm sequence shooting schedule; synopsis and shooting script for "Listen America!" (which became Native Land); outline for editing.
    - no title (Box C226)
      - [One Act Play Magazine, January 1939 issue] (Folder 4)
        Includes a portion of the shooting script for Frontier Films' "Production No. 5," later retitled Native Land.
    - no title (Box C227)
      - [Native Land retrospective clippings, A Harbor Anthology Outline, personal material], ca. 1930; ca. 1941; ca. 1962; 1975 (Folder 2)
        Photograph of Edwin Rolfe; correspondence, articles, and notes about retrospective screenings of Native Land; paper "Cultural Images in Documentaries of the New Deal Era: A Rhetorical Analysis" by Peter C. Rollins; notes labeled "Word and Sound - A Harbor Anthology."
      - Material for scrapbook, 1942-1951 (Folder 5)
        Includes promotional flyers, letters, union testimonials, newspaper clippings, and reviews for Native Land; newspaper clippings about Paul Strand; a brochure from Brandon Films promoting Native Land,People of the Cumberland, and other films; promotional program for a performance of the score of Native Land; and an invitation from the Hollywood Writers Mobilization for a presentation by Joris Ivens and screening of films including Native Land.
      - [Bag labeled: Xeroxes "Scrap Book" --Native Land and Strange Victory], ca. 1942 (Folder 7)
        Copies of newspaper articles, reviews, program, invitation, and quotes from reviews about Native Land[none are about Strange Victory].
      - [Correspondence, film festival applications], 1973 (Folder 20)
        Includes a letter from the University of California, Berkeley, thanking Hurwitz for permission to show Native Land, with articles and a program flyer.
    - no title (Box OS-5)
      - [Tube labeled: Karlovy Vary prize for Native Land], 1949 (Tube Tube 2)
        Tube containing the Karlovy Vary prize for Native Land.
    - no title (Box OS-6)
      - [Native Land and Strange Victory scrapbook], 1941-1942; 1948 (Folder 2)
        Bound scrapbook, very fragile. Contains programs, clippings (English and Hebrew, one with translation), screening notices and invitations, reviews, black and white production photograph, quotes from reviews, tickets, and audience responses for Native Land and Strange Victory. Copy of certificate of participation for Strange Victory in the Venice Film Festival. Copy of W.E.B Du Bois letter about Strange Victory.
      - [Hurwitz, Leo -- Scrapbook materials for Strange Victory and Native Land], 1948; 1961; 1966; 1975 (Folder 2a)
        Notes regarding the scrapbook, clippings about Strange Victory,Native Land, the Eichmann trial, and Hurwitz as artist-in-residence at Hamilton/Kirkland Colleges; a press release for The Sun and Richard Lippold; order form for theater parties for Strange Victory.
  - Subseries 24, On This Day, 1951-1953
    - no title (Box C003)
      - H.I.P. Film – 1952-1953 –On This Day (Folder 4)
        Correspondence, notes, publicity, and production materials for the short film On This Day, produced for H.I.P. (Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York). Includes shooting script, narration script, shooting schedule, recording papers, and logs. Also includes drafts of the shooting script under its original title ("The Fifth Freedom"), written by Ben Kerner.
    - no title (Box C018)
      - [Envelope labeled: Material for scrapbook], 1951; 1953 (Folder 5d)
        Clippings and correspondence concerning An Evening with Richard Rodgers and On This Day.
    - no title (Box C050)
      - Films: Dr.-patient relations, 1953 (Folder 12)
    - no title (Box C233)
      - On This Day, 1952 (Folder 2d)
        Shooting script labeled "Producer's Copy Script" and 7/29/52 Draft Treatment -- Revision of H.I.P. Film.
  - Subseries 25, Opera Television Theatre, 1948-1950
    - no title (Box C108)
      - Current programming, 1950 (Folder 3h)
        Materials related to possible operas adapted television by Souvaine, Co., including lists of suggested operas and singers, and memos regarding production issues. Also includes a list of television properties owned by Souvaine and an outline of special television events produced by the Theatre Guild.
      - [Carmen libretto and clippings], 1950 (Folder 3i)
        Carmen libretto, and clippings regarding Souvaine Co.'s adaptation for Opera Television Theatre.
      - Variety ad, 1950 (Folder 5e)
        Variety ad copy and press notices for Carmen broadcast.
      - Memoranda, 1948; 1950 (Folder 5g)
        Materials related to the television broadcast of La Traviata, including rehearsal schedule and libretto. Also includes Souvaine memos regarding "The Forgotten Years" and contracts.
      - La Traviata, ca. 1950 (Folder 5j)
        Staging outline for the television broadcast of La Traviata.
  - Subseries 26, Pattern of a Profession, 1943-1961; 1953-1959
    - no title (Box C028)
      - [Bound dental film scripts], 1959 (Folder 1)
        Three bound scripts for "A Motion Picture Prepared for the American Dental Association by Dynamic Films, Inc.," later titled Pattern of a Profession.
      - Post-script dentistry, 1959 (Folder 3a)
        Correspondence regarding Pattern of a Profession, with notes. Correspondents include the Harvard School of Dental Medicine, the Lancaster Cleft Palate Clinic, and Lee Bobker.
      - Script draft, 1959 (Folder 3b)
        Revised draft of the Pattern of a Profession script.
      - Notes -- dentistry and outlines, 1958 (Folder 3c)
        "Design of Subject Matter" diagram for Pattern of a Profession.
      - Starts -- dental, 1958-1959 (Folder 3d)
        Research topics related to Pattern of a Profession, including notes on the cleft palate and the public health dentist. Also includes a partial script outline.
      - [Film notebooks], 1958 (Folder 3e)
        Notebooks related to the production of Pattern of a Profession.
      - Trip notes, 1955-1959 (Folder 3f)
        Materials related to the production of Pattern of a Profession, including notes; issue of the New York University (NYU) College of Dentistry Bulletin; a Veterans Administration Dental Internship and Residency Program booklet; a pamphlet entitled "Should You Be a Dentist?"; and a catalog listing of postgraduate and graduate courses in dentistry at NYU.
      - "Research's" notes, 1943; 1955-1958 (Folder 3g)
        Research material related to the production of Pattern of a Profession, including reprinted articles from Scientific American;The Journal of Dental Research;Oral Surgery, Oral Medicine, and Oral Pathology; and The Journal of the American Dental Association.
      - [Envelope labeled: Public health notes], 1954-1959 (Folder 3h)
        Publications related to dental health, including American Dental Association pamphlets; dental flyers and handouts distributed by the city of Hartford; a public affairs pamphlet about adding fluoride to the water; a list of basic recommendations of the Connecticut Advisory School Health Council toward achieving an ideal school dental program; and reprints of journal articles by Dr. Menczer.
      - Chicago "reading" material, 1953-1959 (Folder 3i)
        Material related to dental health, including an issue of Today's Health published by the American Medical Association; a history of the American Dental Association; a schedule for the 1958 Greater New York Dental Meeting; and reprinted articles on dentistry and children's dental care.
      - [Envelope labeled: ADA trip], 1958 (Folder 3j)
        Hurwitz's schedule for the American Dental Association meetings he would attend regarding Pattern of a Profession, with letters of confirmation from secretary Helen R. Kristt.
      - [Pattern of a Profession– script drafts, notes, correspondence], 1959 (Folder 3k)
        Drafts of scripts for Pattern of a Profession dated 2/11/1959 and 3/12/1959, with notes and related correspondence.
    - no title (Box C037)
      - Pattern of a Profession(dental film), 1959 (Folder 1a)
        Two scripts titled "A Motion Picture prepared for The American Dental Association by Dynamic Films, Inc.," written by Hurwitz and dated 2/11/1959. One script contains a production note initialed by Hurwitz.
    - no title (Box C040)
      - Film facilities -- also "general" -- misc. letters, 1956-1961 (Folder 21)
        Personal and professional materials, including correspondence from the Lancaster Cleft Palate Clinic, and correspondence from the American Dental Association regarding the success of Pattern of a Profession and the possibility of a second dental film.
    - no title (Box C055)
      - [Flex folder labeled:Pattern of a Profession copies of scripts], 1959 (Folder 16)
        Seven copies of the script for "A Motion Picture prepared for The American Dental Association by Dynamic Films, Inc.," written by Hurwitz and dated 2/11/1950. Three copies have a "production note" insert, and one copy is marked "With ADA revisions & with /Bob Ker's[?] deletions in cleft-palate seq."
  - Subseries 27, "Pay Day,", 1937-1939
    - no title (Box C192)
      - [Envelope labeled: Notes, etc. of '30s -- early Frontier], 1937-1939 (Folder 2b)
        Includes a two-ring binder with "Victory" embossed on the cover containing sequences for film labeled "Prologue -- XX -- Song of the School-Children," with notes on child labor film ("Pay Day").
      - [Envelope labeled: "Pay Day" -- child labor script], ca. 1938 (Folder 3c)
        Bound copy of the script for "Pay Day: A Story of Child Labor" by Vera Caspary and George Sklar (with notes throughout), outline of the film, and shooting script.
  - Subseries 28, "Peter Pan,", 1950-1951
    - no title (Box C024)
      - [Peter Pan script], 1950 (Folder 2)
        Script for the 1950 stage version of Peter Pan, with notes in Hurwitz's hand.
    - no title (Box C034)
      - ["Peter Pan" plot and music outlines], 1951; undated (Folder 2a)
        "Peter Pan" plot outline; list of music tracks, with side (scene) numbers and times.
      - [Sc]ript "Peter Pan", 1951 (Folder 2b)
        Television script for "Peter Pan" by Hurwitz, dated 12/14/1951, with explanation of the show's cancellations written on cover page.
      - TV Script (work) "Peter Pan", undated (Folder 2c)
        Two undated script drafts of "Peter Pan," with notations.
    - no title (Box C049)
      - "Peter Pan" original play script, ca. 1950 (Folder 14)
        Plastic bag labeled "Peter Pan -- Original play-script," containing bound copy of the script used in the 1950-1951 Broadway production of Peter Pan, produced by Peter Lawrence, with music by Leonard Bernstein, and starring Jean Arthur and Boris Karloff.
  - SUBSERIES NAME, 1931-1937
    - no title (Box C192)
      - [Bound folder labeled:Plow that Broke the Plains], 1935 (Folder 2c)
        Bound pages in folder labeled "General Statements: Spoliation of the Land" with clippings about the dust bowl pasted on the pages. Tucked inside are: shooting script for "Resettlement Film #1" by Ralph Steiner, Hurwitz, and Paul Strand, submitted to Pare Lorentz (with handwritten draft); "Dust Blowing" article from Harper's Monthly Magazine; article on Lorentz from Scribner's magazine.
      - [Folder labeled: Misc. stuff of the thirties], 1931-1937 (Folder 2d.2)